<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lateral Thunking (Posts about economics)</title><link>http://brianbaquiran.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://brianbaquiran.github.io/categories/economics.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2020 09:32:10 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Why Governments Block Startups</title><link>http://brianbaquiran.github.io/posts/why-governments-block-startups/</link><dc:creator>Brian Baquiran</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of permits and regulations needed in order to open a hotel, in the same way there are regulations needed to open a taxi franchise. This is a major barrier to new entrants in these markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's in the interests of the entrenched  &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;(hotel|taxi)&lt;/code&gt; franchisees to have this barrier to new entrants as high as possible, since they're already past it. So they lobby and push government to enforce and even make the barrier even higher for new entrants in order to preserve their hold over the market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, of course, stifles competition and decreases innovation. It gets ridiculous when even plumbers, manicurists, and barbers need certification and licensing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It's always in the interests of entrenched players to increase regulation. Whenever you see regulations, certification and licensing required, it usually indicates a stagnant industry ripe for disruption.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>economics</category><category>startups</category><guid>http://brianbaquiran.github.io/posts/why-governments-block-startups/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 14:56:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Programmers don't understand Economics</title><link>http://brianbaquiran.github.io/posts/programmers-dont-understand-economics/</link><dc:creator>Brian Baquiran</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://phackers.slack.com/"&gt;phackers slack&lt;/a&gt; #careeradvice channel, a recurring theme seems to be the higher salaries that developers overseas are paid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It always starts out with a developer -- usually a novice but not always -- discovering that developers in some other country with the same skillset as him are getting paid 5x (or whatever multiple) he is getting here. Other developers will then helpfully remind him of the greater cost-of-living, higher taxes, etc. in those countries. Invariably someone will say that Pinoy developers are worth more than what they're getting now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, here's an important concept that I have had to explain multiple times:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're worth whatever the market determines you're worth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People often forget or ignore the fact that it's not just them and the employer that are negotiating. It's other employers, AND other workers. If you're negotiating with company, do you honestly think you're the only candidate they're considering? Other candidates or applicants may have the same skillset as you, but offer to work for a lower salary (for whatever reason). Other workers competing for the same jobs determine what you'll end up getting as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real way to command a higher rate, regardless of whether it's local employment or remote, is to be as &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;@mparaz&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;@radeinla&lt;/code&gt; put it, the special snowflake. If you're a commodity programmer, you get the commodity programmer rate because there are so many other candidates with the same or similar skillset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="He's been out of the job market for a while." class="align-center" src="http://brianbaquiran.github.io/images/liam_neeson_skills.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have, or can &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signalling_(economics)"&gt;signal&lt;/a&gt; that you have &lt;cite&gt;a particular set of skills&lt;/cite&gt; and there is a demand for those skills, then congrats, special snowflake, you can command a higher rate. The more difficult to obtain those skills (or signals) are, and the greater the demand, the better able you will be to command a higher rate whether here or abroad.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>career</category><category>economics</category><category>salaries</category><guid>http://brianbaquiran.github.io/posts/programmers-dont-understand-economics/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2017 23:06:41 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>